Inventory of the Garrett Family Papers 1786-1928
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Letters, 1825-1928, n.d. (Box 1-2)
  - Letters, 1850-1859., 26 items. (Box-folder 1:4-6)
    - J.R. Underwood, n.p., to [Thomas H.] Bailey [sic], n.p., n.d., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Describes the laws regarding the sale of land for taxes; advises his friend to hire an agent to determine when the lands were sold and whether the sales were regular; recommends his son Eugene Underwood as the man to investigate the matter if the lands lay south of the Green River and are military land.
      This letter was included within the above letter; Th[omas] H. Bayly, Washington, to A[lexander] C. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 22 Aug[ust 18]50.
    - R.R. Garrett, Marl Banks, to son Geo[rge] R. Garrett, Richmond College, Richmond, Virginia, 8 Nov[embe]r 1850., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Is glad to hear he likes his school; advises him to "be studious, steady and moral, for your course will be watched with an eagle's eye"; reminds him that he should obey the rules and regulations for his school, for otherwise all his efforts to be good will fail; informs him that Mr. S.G. Cook received his letter and was pleased to hear from him; praises the letter he wrote to Penny as being the "best written and dictated letter I have yet seen from you"; admonishes him to not "be led off from the path of rectitude by vicious young men, or the temptations by which you are surrounded"; will only bring in a half crop of corn this year as the crops are not doing well; sends the love of family and friends.
    - Thomas Palentini[?], Richmond, [Virginia], to Mr. Alex[ander C.] Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 11 Nov[ember] 1850., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Asks that if he has received any money from Mr. Cooke or from Mr. W[illia]m Jones to please forward it to him; notices that Mr. [?] is not at college this year and requests him to see if he can procure the $15 dollars he owes him; has written to Mr. Henry Porter, who owes him $12, instructing him to give the money to him [ACG].
    - A[lexander] C. Garrett, Richmond, [Virginia], to "brother" Dr. Ro[bert] M. Garrett, W[illia]msburg, Virginia, 17 Dec[embe]r 1850., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Wishes he had received his letter sooner as it would have persuaded more people to vote for his side; informs him that his side won the vote by eighteen votes and that "the question is now considered settled -- we hear men of all parties speak of the Bill as the law of the land"; mentions that Southall feigned illness to try to postpone the debate; believes that the Bill will certainly pass on Thursday or Friday; will go with the rest of the Democrats, save for "that red headed Montague from Middlesex who will vote against us," to the Governor to demand that the Democrats be given control of the Board of Directors; wonders why Saunders & Co. read such an unwise remonstrance before the public body; sends Barlow some extra copies of the Examiner as the editor published the remarks without their knowledge; informs him that the Enquirer will also take notice of this subject; asks that he see if he can find the $30 in his desk drawer and send it to him.
    - Geo[rge] T. Williamson, Cincinnati, [Ohio], to A[lexander] C. Garrett, n.p., 21 Jan[uar]y 1851., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Informs him that during the sale of a portion of land by Mr. P. Pumphrey to the late W.T. Galt of Williamsburgh [sic], he found that some parts of this land were sold for taxes that had been left for the heirs of N. Fox Sr.; mentions that each heir, including Nat Fox and Henry Fox, were entitled to 355.5 acres; will find out where Nat Fox and Henry Fox lived and died in Ohio; feels the Tax Title under which these lands are held is very strong, but will try to save a sum for the heirs.
    - Alexander C. Garrett, White Sulphur Springs, to "sister," n.p., 27 August 1851., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Describes all the ladies at White Sulphur Springs and mentions Miss Izetta Coles as "a belle who rings to the tune of $60,000"; mentions a party of South Carolinians and Floridians and describes all in the party; believes the belle of White Sulphur is a Miss Bowyer of Botetourt, to whom he has been paying attention; assures her there is nothing serious in that arena for "why be 'college larnt' and let a simple mountain maid fool me"; mentions the Presidential party and in particular Mr. Corcoran, "the great banker from Washington and who is the money changer of the Presidential party," as also paying attention to Miss Bowyer; is smug that youth has won over money in the matter of Miss Bowyer but is aware that he needs to moderate his attentions; mentions that Miss Bowyer is either in love with him or is simply carrying on a harmless flirtation; has been slightly ill and believes it due to drinking too much of the water.
    - A[lexander] C. Garrett, Sweet Springs, to "brother" [Dr. Robert M. Garrett?], n.p., 3 September 1851., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Informs him that Governor Floyd is anxiously seeking the nomination from the Staunton Convention; was approached by P.H. Aylitt, an editor of the Richmond Examiner, with an offer to allow him [ACG] to choose the Board of Directors for the Lunatic Asylum in Williamsburg if he could secure the vote for Floyd in Williamsburg, York County, and James City County; was offered head of the Board of Directors under this plan; has decided to go with this offer and asks whom should be appointed to the Board; has "rather a difficult game to play" as Johnson also wants his support for Governor; would like to support Judge Christian for judge of their circuit; would like to run for the legislature as "there is nothing like office to give a man influence 'with the powers that be'"; afraid that Segar will defeat him; had $200 stolen from him and asks that he send $16 or $20 to him at Staunton.
    - A.F. Leonard[?], Norfo[lk, Virginia], to Robert Garrett, Williamsburg, [Virginia], 3 Nov[ember] 1851., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Writes on behalf of Mr. N. Pumphrey; informs him that the real estate formerly belonging to W[illia]m R. Pumphrey that he [RG] has advertised for sale is part of the trust deed from Pumphrey to Jno. M. Gregory and so now belongs to Gregory.
    - W[illiam] Lyttleton Savage, Philadelphia, [Penn.], to "sister," n.p., 12 Dec[embe]r 1851., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Was sorry to hear his brother's severe and painful attack; sends a prescription of living solely on oatmeal porridge for six weeks; did not send marble hearths and casings for the upstairs rooms because he feels that would be too expensive; discusses the possibility of sending his slave, John, to help his brother, "Say to my brother I am very willing, for him to have John as long as he wishes him, provided John is willing to go to the Western Shore,...I am perfectly willing, but I cannot compel him to separate from his friends and wife...and if John is willing I am not only willing, but desirous that my brother should have him as long as he lives;" shares his views on the treatment of slaves as "conscientious;" owns no ploughboy of the kind that his brother would like, being that his other slaves are unsuitable, George is too young and Harry is too old; speaks of other furnishings for the house that he has procured for her; sends a total of the amount of money he has paid so far.
    - Two letters written on the same page, 3 March 1852., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Maria L. Savage, Eyre Ville, to "mother" Lauretta [?], n.p., 3 March 1852. Has been visiting relatives and friends; shares news of all with whom she is staying; has read "Wide Wide World" and enjoyed it; believes she and Father would enjoy it as well; is afraid Father did not receive the basket she made; feels er basket was well done for a first attempt. 3 pp. ALS.
      Also contains the letter of: Lucy [?], n.p., to Aunt Lauretta [?], n.p., n.d. Informs her of the death of Colonel Lucad of Accomac from pneumonia; asks her to write when she [Lucy] gets to Washington. 2 pp. ALS.
    - Ellen [?], Hern Cliffs, to "aunt" Lauretta [?], n.p., 29 March 1852., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Shares a great deal of news of friends and family; asks her to tell Uncle Thom[as?] many things about the family; misses them both a great deal.
    - W[illiam] F. & Thomas Ritchie, Richmond, [Virginia], to R.R. Garrett, Yorktown, Virginia, 22 Sept[ember] 1852., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Seeks to approximate the Presidential election and asks him to send the probable vote of his county; would also like to know how to vote would compare to last fall's vote for Governor.
    - W. Goddin, Richm[on]d, [Virginia], to A[lexander C.] Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 8 Nov[ember] 1852., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Has employed Mr. Thomas M. Ladd to survey where Mrs. Richardson lives; informs him that Mr. Ladd will be there several days, when it would be a good time for him [ACG] to visit there also.
    - Two letters written on the same page, 2 December 1852., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Susie [?], Hern Cliffs, to "aunt" Lauretta [?], n.p., 2 December 1852. Intends to walk to Kendall Grove today, and must start early as it is five miles away; was disappointed that Uncle William arrived without Uncle Thomas; informs her that Uncle Thomas "is a sorry farmer not to have his corn gathered before this," but will excuse him since he has had the rheumatism; Father will not let Rob go to see them [Lauretta] this year until his lungs get stronger; believes General Nottingham has gone deranged on the subject of religion, but it will soon pass; informs her that this week is her last in her family's house, as it is being sold; believes Father will settle in Washington; supposes she has heard of the death of Cousin Ellen Burbridge. 3 pp. ALS.
      Also contains the letter of: Susan E. Wilson to Lauretta [?], n.p., n.d. Feels in such confusion that she is not sure what she has written or what she wants to say; informs her that the house is to be sold on the fifteenth of the month, when they will sell everything, and possession must be given on the first of January; mentions William Savage's departure the next day for Philadelphia; had hoped to see her, but Mr. Wilson seems to think he will be able to visit her soon. 1 p. ALS.
    - B[enjamin] F. Garrett, Ho[use of] Delegates, to Alex[ander C. Garrett], n.p., 9 Dec[embe]r 1852., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Describes the praise that his [ACG] speech has received from various members, including Segar and W[illia]m Ritchie; informs him that the editor of the Whig will publish it next week; regrets that he cannot come home until after Christmas because the Internal Improvement Bills come up next Saturday; hopes that he [ACG] will be able to come up before then; asks him to tell Ma that he intended to visit her but circumstances prevented him; will bring Maria and Mary to visit Ma.
    - W[illia]m H. Ammon, Henrico County, [Virginia], to Alexander C. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 11 Feb[ruary] 1853., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Had heard from Mr. M. Bishop that the suit between himself and Pumphrey had been settled in his [WHA] favor; asks him to write and give him all the details; asks if he [?] has taken the Tho[mas] W. contract and if Whitaker has paid the money on the contract; would like to see him the next time he comes to Richmond; misses Dr. G[arrett] in the practice of his family; has had several Negroes sick and has suffered from a bad cold himself.
    - W[illiam] W. Coke, Princess Anne Court House, [Virginia], to Col. Alexander C. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 16 Feb[ruary] 1853., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Had written to him about the appointment as Physician for the Marine Hospital of Dr. W.P. Morgan; would like to add the amendment of his appointment in the event of the removal of the present incumbent; feels that his [ACG] compliance will place him under many obligations to him; asks about the rich Irishman that died in Halifax Co. without heirs; would like to know all the information as he thinks he will be able to find his heirs in Ireland through correspondence with lawyers in Cork, Ireland.
    - Newton Short, n.p., to Alexander C. Garret [sic], Williamsburg, Virginia, 21 March [18]53., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Postmarked Richmond, Virginia Has heard from Mr. Saunders that he [ACG] has been authorized to put his claim against Nelson's estate before the court; has a receipt for the bond held by Mr. Saunders from Mr. Nelson.
    - W[illia]m H. Ammon, Henrico [County, Virginia], to Alex[ander C. Garrett], n.p., 8 August 1853., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Assumes that Mr. Whitaker has not yet paid the bond he [WHA] left with Garrett; asks him to inform Mr. Whitaker that he is not in compliance with his promise; would like a check on Richmond Bank if he is successful in getting the money; asks for news from Philadelphia.
    - B[enjamin] F. Garrett, Mt. Laurel Post Office, Halifax County, [Virginia], to Ellie [Alexander C. Garrett], n.p., 14 Octo[ber] 1853., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Has not written due to wrapping up his former business as he intends to quit the practice; feels it impossible to make it to Williamsburg at any given time; has pulled their house down and intends to build another; and Maria is at the Court House visiting her uncle Bailey during this time; is willing that he and brother Robert divides the slaves between them and asks if he needs to be present during this time; encloses a letter from Francis H. Lee and asks if he will find out from Mr. Lee whether he wants to advertise the selling of the property according to the deed; informs him the railroad will be finished to Clover Depot, near his home, by the first of February.
    - W[illia]m Lyttleton Savage, Philadelphia, [Penn.], to "brother" [?], n.p., 23 Jan[uar]y 1855., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Agrees with the suggestion in Maria's letter that he ["brother"] take a trip to Northampton in order to convalesce and recover from his illness; has not been well himself, and has been suffering from a disease that resembles bilious cholic, and supposes it was combined also with gout; was truly sorry to hear of the loss suffered by Dr. and Mrs. Garrett [the death of one of their daughters]; informs him of the death of Mr. Lyon, who passed away peacefully and retained his faculties up to within a few hours of his death; hopes that he and his wife may decide to move to Williamsburg.
    - W[illia]m P. Nottingham, Eastville, [Virginia], to [his sister] Lauretta [Savage], n.p., 3 May 1855., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Expresses deepest sympathy for the loss of [her husband] W. Savage; was shocked by Savage's change in health when he saw him last; asks her to inform Dr. Garrett that he is to travel to Norfolk next Tuesday and will meet Garrett there; sends the love of the family.
    - Jno. [John] E. Winder, Eastville, [Virginia], to "sister" [?], n.p., 14 Aug[us]t 1858., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Received her last letter without a signature or a date; informs her that Uncle Sam's violin is beyond repair; would not sell Pa's violin but if she would like Rob to have it, he will lend it to him; encloses $45 to settle the bill with Mr. Kellum.
    - B[enjamin] F. Garrett, Clover Station, to Dr. Ro[bert] M. Garrett, n.p., 14 Jan[uary] 1859., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Has filled his ice house with ice three inches thick; killed his hogs, which averaged 225 lbs. each; has taken all his Negroes to his new plantation that he intends to make the finest in the county; is determined to make a good farmer; asks after all the news, especially of the Asylum, who the candidates are for the Senate and the House of Delegates, and whether there is no opposition to Garrett for Congress; informs him that Mr. Clark gave Bettie 15 Negroes and $3,000.
    - Two letters written on the same page, 22-23 May 1859., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      S[?] Guion, [?] of Virginia, to "aunt" [?], n.p., 22 May 1859. Informs her that Robertson is in love with a certain black-eyed lady, whose name he cannot yet reveal. 2 pp. ALS.
      Also contains the letter of: S[?] Guion, [?] of Virginia, to "aunt" [?], n.p., 23 May 1859. Regrets that he could not finish the letter the night before, but he was overcome by sleep; reveals that he will come to Williamsburg soon to become engaged; informs her that the weather has been quite warm; shares news of the family. 3 pp. ALS.
    - W[illia]m Lyon, Richmond, [Virginia], to Dr. [Robert M. Garrett], n.p., 31 Oct[ober] 1859., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Encloses a check for $5, the amount of Mrs. Saunders' donation to the Bible Society of Virginia; informs him that the money is also intended as the first payment toward making George T. Wilson, son of Rev. G.T. Wilson, a life member; thanks him for the kind care he received while a houseguest at his home.
  - Letters, 1860-1869., 20 items. (Box-folder 1:7-8)
    - M. T. Hughes, Prince Edward C[ourt] Ho[use], [Virginia], to Dr. Rob[er]t M. Garrett, n.p., 8 Jan[uary] 1860., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Encloses a note to him; hopes that he will accede to his wishes.
    - B[enjamin] F. Garrett, Clover Station, [Virginia], to "brother" [Dr. Robert M. Garrett], n.p., 28 Jan[uary] 1860., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Informs him that Mary has been extremely sick for a week, but it appears that she is recovering; will return home next week if she continues to improve; regrets that he has no concrete information to give him regarding Mr. Hughes; advises him that if Lou has made up her mind about Hughes, that there is little he can do to stop the wedding; was sorry to hear of the death of A.C. McCandlish but was told by Robby that his habits were bad.
    - Bettie A. Garrett, Chester, to "sister" Susan [Winder Garrett], n.p., 27 Feb[ruary] 1860., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Has heard of Lou's impending marriage but is concerned that she is a bit young, being not yet twenty; assures her that Mary is quite recovered and has an enormous appetitite; Mr. Garrett has gone up to Court today, so she will have three or four servants to sleep in the house and protect her and the baby; informs her that the baby is getting fatter every day, but still has no teeth; asks after her garden and shares news on her own gardening.
    - Two letters written on the same page, 29 February [18]60., pages. (Box-folder 1:7)
      P.W. Garrett, n.p., to "uncle" Robert [M. Garrett], n.p., 29 February [18]60. Has waited to write till Lou settled on a date for her wedding, which will be on the 25th of April; was told by Mr. Hughes that he intends to meet him in Richmond; informs him that Lou could not do with less than $300 for the wedding; was told by Mama that the interest on the money earned from the sale of the servants along with what brother owes for Negro hires would be more than $300; asks if [cousin] Laura has yet gone to the Eastern Shore as they expect her every day. 3 pp. ALS.
      Also contains the letter of: Mary Lou Garrett, n.p., to "uncle" [Robert M. Garrett], n.p., n.d. Believes that $300 would not be even half enough for her wedding; assures him that she cannot do with less than $1500; sends love to Aunt Sue and the children; asks to have him send the $1500 as Mama agrees that it is not too much. 2 pp.
    - B[enjamin] F. Garrett, Clover Station, [Virginia], to Col. Alex[ander] C. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 17 July 1860., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Reports that his wheat crop has been damaged by a hailstorm and fears he will get only a half a crop; hopes for rain because otherwise he will not make a good crop of corn or tobacco; discusses politics and who will be elected; informs him that his ankle is no better and hopes that he can send the "receipt" he made for his leg; has decided to go to White Sulphur [Springs] this summer.
    - W[illia]m P. Nottingham, Eastville, [Virginia], to [his sister] Lauretta [Savage], n.p. 4 pp. ALS. 25 Mar[ch 18]60[?]., pages. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Has just received the interest on her two bonds from the Messrs. Nottingham; has been expecting her to visit but realizes she does not know yet when she will be able to; hopes that her children have passed the critical point of scarlet fever and are now safely convalescing; informs her that he and Comfort are suffering from bad colds; shares the news that Hamilton Neale and Lizzy Smith are to be married this summer, and Rob[ert] Nottingham and Miss Byrd are to be married at length also; informs her that the new steamer Northampton is to make her first stop on this shore tomorrow, and on which one may safely and comfortably cross the bay.
    - Jno. [John E. Winder], Norfolk, [Virginia], to "sister" [Susan Winder Garrett?], n.p., 25 April 1860., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Has not had time to make the inquiries she wanted; deposited $100.66 in her account to bring her balance to $574.59; has not heard from [?] Guion; will send the ring she spoke of if he finds it; informs her that Mrs. Galt is in Norfolk staying at the Atlantic Hotel.
    - [W. Robertson Garrett], Williamsburg, [Virginia], to "aunty" [?], n.p., August 1860[?]., 2 pages. ALS. Incomplete. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Spent about a week dividing his time between Norfolk and Hampton and saw the Great Eastern; was appointed a delegate to the Democratic convention at Charlottesville as soon as he returned; rode up to the convention with Miss Maggie Parker and plans to go see her in September on the Eastern Shore when all the rest of her beaux have departed.
    - E. Pettis, Edgewood, to "madam" [Susan Winder Garrett], n.p., 13 Nov[ember] 1860., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Seeks to gain the vote of [W.] Robertson [Garrett] for Tallie's husband [?]; is afraid that the man will lose his office, and he has no other means of employment; informs her that Eliza's health has been poor lately; will not be able to make it down this winter as Eliza is taking care of some little servants who have lost their mother, and she is afraid that they will be mistreated if she leaves them; has had a severe attack which makes him more aware of his age and his mortality.
    - J.A. Smith, Farmer's Bank of Virginia, Richmond, to Mr. Ro[bert] M. Garrett, W[illia]m[s]burg, [Virginia], 31 Jan[uar]y 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Returns Humphrey's and Taliaferro's check for $150 to him as it was not endorsed; informs him that there was no deposit made to his credit at that bank.
    - [W.] Robertson [Garrett], Young's Mill, [Virginia], to "father" [Dr. Robert M. Garrett], n.p., 9 Oct[ober] 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Reported to General McClaws [McLaws] last Monday and was stationed at Young's farm at the mouth of the Warwick River; occupies the right of the line of defenses and is in command of the right battery; was told by General McClaws [McLaws] that General Magruder wished to take New-Ports News [Newport News], but there are 11,000 men stationed at that place and there is little chance for a fight; will take winter quarters nearby.
    - B[enjamin F. Garrett, Clover Station, [Virginia], to "brother" [Dr. Robert M. Garrett], n.p., 3 Dec[embe]r 1862., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)